part 2 chapter 3.
We can come here once again,' said Julia.
'It's generally safe to use any Hideout twice. But not for another month or two, of course.'
As soon as she woke up her demeanor had changed. She became alert and
business-like put her clothes on not at the scarlet sash about her waist and
began arranging the details of the journey home.
It seemed natural to leave this to her.
She obviously had a practical cunning which Winston lacked, and she seemed also
to have an exhaustive knowledge of the countryside around London, stored away
from innumerable community hikes.
The route she gave him was quite different from the one by which he had
come, and brought him out at a different railway station.
'Never go home the same way as you went out,' she said, as though enunciating an
important general principle.
She would leave first, and Winston was to wait half an hour before following her.
She had named a place where they could meet after work, four evenings hence.
It was a street in one of the poorer quarters, where there was an open market
which was generally crowded and noisy.
She would be hanging about among the stalls, pretending to be in search of
shoelaces or sewing thread If she judged that the coast was clear
she would blow her nose when he approached: otherwise he was to walk past
her without recognition.
But with luck, in the middle of the crowd, it would be safe to talk for a quarter
of an hour and arrange another meeting.
'And now I must go,' she said as soon as he had mastered his instructions. 'I'm due
back at 1930. I've got to put in two hours for the Junior Anti-Sex League,
handing out leaflets, or something.
Isn't it bloody?
Give me a brush down would you. Have I got any twigs in my hair? Are you sure?
Then goodbye my love goodbye flung herself into his arms, kissed him
almost violently, and a moment later pushed her way through the saplings and
disappeared into the wood with very little noise. Even now he had not found
out her surname or her address.
However, it made no difference, for it was inconceivable that they could ever meet
indoors or exchange any kind of written communication.
As it happened they never went back to the clearing in the wood.
During the month of May there was only one further occasion on which they
actually succeeded in making love.
That was in another Hiding Place known to Julia, the belfry of a ruinous church
in an almost deserted stretch of country where an atomic bomb had fallen 30 years earlier.
It was a good hiding place when once you got there, but the getting there was very dangerous.
For the rest they could meet only in the streets, in a different place every
evening and never for more than half an hour at a time.
In the street it was usually possible to talk, after a fashion.
As they drifted down the crowded pavements, not quite abreast and never
looking at one another, they carried on a curious, intermittent conversation which
flicked on and off like the beams of a lighthouse, suddenly nipped into silence
by the approach of a Party uniform or the proximity of a telescreen, then taken
up again minutes later in the middle of a sentence, then abruptly cut short as
they parted at the agreed spot, then continued almost without introduction on the following day.
Julia appeared to be quite used to this kind of conversation, which he called
'talking by installments She was also surprisingly adept at
speaking without moving her lips. Just once in almost a month of nightly
meetings they managed to exchange a kiss.
They were passing in silence down a side street Julia would never speak when they
were away from the main streets) when there was a deafening roar, the earth
heaved and the air darkened, and Winston found himself lying on his side, bruised
and terrified. A rocket bomb must have dropped quite near at hand.
Suddenly he became aware of Julia's face a few centimeters from his own, deathly
white, as white as chalk. Even her lips were white.
She was dead! He clasped her against him and found that he was kissing a live warm face.
But there was some powdery stuff that got in the way of his lips.
Both of their faces were thickly coated with plaster.
There were evenings when they reached their rendezvous and then had to walk
past one another without a sign, because a patrol had just come around the corner
or a helicopter was hovering overhead.
Even if it had been less dangerous, it would still have been difficult to find time to meet.
Winston's working week was 60 hours Julius was even longer, and their free
days varied according to the pressure of work and did not often coincide.
Julia, in any case, seldom had an evening completely free.
She spent an astonishing amount of time in attending lectures and demonstrations,
distributing literature for the Junior Anti-Sex League, preparing banners for
Hate Week, making collections for the savings campaign, and such like activities
page he said; it was camouflage. If you kept the small rules you could break the
big ones. She even induced Winston to mortgage yet another of his evenings by
enrolling himself for the part-time munition work which was done voluntarily
by zealous Party members.
So, one evening every week, Winston spent four hours of paralyzing boredom,
screwing together small bits of metal which were probably parts of bomb fuses,
in a drafty ill-lit Workshop where the knocking of hammers mingled drearily
with the music of the telescreens.
When they met in the church tower the gaps in their fragmentary conversation
were filled up. It was a blazing afternoon. The air in the little square
chamber above the bells was hot and stagnant, and smelt overpoweringly of pigeon dung
They sat talking for hours on the dusty twig-litted floor, one or other of them
getting up from time to time to cast a glance through the arrow slits and to
make sure that no one was coming.
Julia was 26 years old. She lived in a hostel with 30 other girls ('Always in the
stink of women! How I hate women!' she said parenthetically),
and she worked, as he had guessed, on the novel writing machines in the Fiction Department.
She enjoyed her work, which consisted chiefly in running and servicing a
powerful but tricky electric motor.
She was 'not clever', but was fond of using her hands and felt at home with machinery.
She could describe the whole process of composing a novel, from the general
directive issued by the Planning Committee down to the final touching up
by the Rewrite Squad. But she was not interested in the finished product.
She 'didn't much care for reading', she said.
Books were just a commodity that had to be produced, like jam or boot laces
She had no memories of anything before the early 60s and the only person she
had ever known who talked frequently of the days before the Revolution was a
grandfather who had disappeared when she was eight. At school she had been captain
of the hockey team and had won the gymnastics trophy two years running.
She had been a troop leader in the Spies and a branch secretary in the Youth
League before joining the Junior Anti-Sex League.
She had always born an excellent character. She had even (an infallible
mark of good reputation) been picked out to work in pornosek
the subsection of the Fiction Department which turned out cheap pornography for
distribution among the proles.
It was nicknamed Muck House by the people who worked in it, she remarked.
There she had remained for a year, helping to produce booklets in sealed
packets with titles like Spanking Stories or One Night in a Girls' School,
to be bought furtively by proletarian youths who were under the impression
that they were buying something illegal.
'What are these books like?' said Winston curiously. 'Oh, ghastly rubbish. They're
boring, really. They only have six plots, but they swap them around a bit.
Of course I was only on the kaleidoscopes. I was never in the Rewrite
Squad. I'm not literary, dear— —not even enough for that.'
He learned with astonishment that all the workers in ponosec except the heads
of the departments were girls.
The theory was that men, whose sex instincts were less controllable than
those of women, were in greater danger of being corrupted by the filth they handled.
'They don't even like having married women there,' she added. 'Girls are always
supposed to be so pure.
Here's one who isn't, anyway.'
She had had her first love affair when she was 16 with a Party member of 60 who
later committed suicide to avoid arrest.
'And a good job too,' said Julia, 'otherwise they'd have had my name out of him when
he confessed.'
Since then there had been various others.
Life as she saw it was quite simple. You wanted a good time; 'they', meaning the
Party, wanted to stop you having it; you broke the rules as best you could. She
seemed to think it just as natural that 'they' should want to rob you of your
pleasures is that you should want to avoid being caught.
She hated the Party, and said so in the crudest words, but she made no general
criticism of it.
Except where it touched upon her own life she had no interest in Party doctrine.
He noticed that she never used Newspeak words, except the ones that had passed
into everyday use. She had never heard of the Brotherhood, and refused to believe
in its existence.
Any kind of organized revolt against the Party, which was bound to be a failure,
struck her as stupid.
The clever thing was to break the rules and stay alive all the same.
He wondered vaguely how many others like her there might be in the younger
generation— —people who had grown up in the world of the Revolution, knowing
nothing else, accepting the Party as something unalterable, like the sky, not
rebelling against its authority but simply evading it, as a rabbit dodges a dog.
They did not discuss the possibility of getting married. It was too remote to be
worth thinking about.
No imaginable committee would ever sanction such a marriage even if
Catherine Winston's wife, could somehow have been got rid of.
It was hopeless even as a daydream.
'What was she like, your wife?' said Julia.
'She was— —do you know the new speak word good thinkful Meaning naturally orthodox, incapable of
thinking a bad thought?'
'No, I didn't know the word, but I know the kind of person, right enough.'
He began telling her the story of his married life, but curiously enough she
appeared to know the essential parts of it already.
She described to him, almost as though she had seen or felt it, the stiffening
of Catherine's body as soon as he touched her, the way in which she still
seemed to be pushing him from her with all her strength, even when her arms were
clasped tightly around him.
With Julia he felt no difficulty in talking about such things Catherine in
any case, had long ceased to be a painful memory and became merely a distasteful one.
'I could have stood it if it hadn't been for one thing,' he said. He told her about
the frigid little ceremony that Catherine had forced him to go through
on the same night every week.
'She hated it, but nothing would make her stop doing it. She used to call it— —but
you'll never guess.'
'Our duty to the Party,' said Julia promptly.
'How did you know that?'
'I've been at school too, dear. Sex talks once a month for the over 16s And in the
Youth Movement. They rub it into you for years. I dare say it works in a lot of
cases. But of course you can never tell; people are such hypocrites.'
She began to enlarge upon the subject.
With Julia, everything came back to her own sexuality.
As soon as this was touched upon in any way she was capable of Greater cuteness
Unlike Winston, she had grasped the inner meaning of the Party's sexual puritanism.
It was not merely that the sex instinct created a world of its own which was
outside the Party's control and which therefore had to be destroyed if possible.
What was more important was that sexual privation induced hysteria, which was
desirable because it could be transformed into war fever and leader worship
The way she put it was: 'When you make love you're using up
energy; and afterwards you feel happy and don't give a damn for anything.
They can't bear you to feel like that.
They want you to be bursting with energy all the time.
All this marching up and down and cheering and waving flags is simply sex gone sour.
If you're happy inside yourself, why should you get excited about Big Brother
and the Three-Year Plans and the Two Minutes Hate and all the rest of their bloody rot?'
That was very true, he thought. There was a direct, intimate connection between
chastity and political orthodoxy. For how could the fear, the hatred and the
lunatic credulity which the Party needed in its members be kept at the right
pitch, except by bottling down some powerful instinct and using it as a driving force?
The sex impulse was dangerous to the Party, and the Party had turned into
account. They had played a similar trick with the instinct of parenthood.
The family could not actually be abolished, and, indeed, people were
encouraged to be fond of their children in almost the old-fashioned way.
The children, on the other hand, were systematically turned against their
parents and taught to spy on them and report their deviations.
The family had become in effect an extension of the Thought Police. It was a
device by means of which everyone could be surrounded night and day by informers
who knew him intimately.
Abruptly his mind went back to Catherine Catherine would unquestionably have
denounced him to the Thought Police if she had not happened to be too stupid to
detect the unorthodoxy of his opinions.
But what really recalled her to him at this moment was the stifling heat of the
afternoon, which had brought the sweat out on his forehead. He began telling
Julia of something that had happened, or rather had failed to happen, on another
sweltering summer afternoon 11 years ago.
It was three or four months after they were married. They had lost their way on
a community hike somewhere in Kent. They had only lagged behind the others for a
couple of minutes, but they took a wrong turning, and presently found themselves
pulled up short by the edge of an old chalk quarry.
It was a sheer drop of 10 or 20 meters with boulders at the bottom. There was
nobody of whom they could ask the way.
As soon as she realized that they were lost Catherine became very uneasy.
To be away from the noisy mob of hikers even for a moment gave her a feeling of
wrongdoing She wanted to hurry back by the way they had come and start searching in the
other direction.
But at this moment Winston noticed some tufts of loose strife growing in the
cracks of the cliff beneath them.
One tuft was of two colors magenta and brick red apparently growing on the same route
He had never seen anything of the kind before, and he called to Catherine to
come and look at it.
'Look Catherine Look at those flowers.
That clumped down near the bottom. Do you see they're two different colors
She had already turned to go, but she did rather fretfully come back for a moment.
She even leaned out over the cliff face to see where he was pointing. He was
standing a little behind her, and he put his hand on her waist to steady her. At
this moment it suddenly occurred to him how completely alone they were.
There was not a human creature anywhere, not a leaf stirring, not even a bird awake.
In a place like this the danger that there would be a hidden microphone was
very small, and even if there was a microphone it would only pick up sounds.
It was the hottest, sleepiest hour of the afternoon.
The sun blazed down upon them, the sweat tickled his face. And the thought struck him....
'Why didn't you give her a good shove?'
said Julia. 'I would have.'
'Yes, dear, you would have. I would if I'd
been the same person then as I am now. Or perhaps I would— —I'm not certain.'
'Are you sorry you didn't?'
'Yes. On the whole I'm sorry I didn't.'
They were sitting side by side on the dusty floor.
He pulled her closer against him. Her head rested on his shoulder, the pleasant
smell of her hair conquering the pigeon dung She was very young, he thought, she still
expected something from life, she did not understand that to push an inconvenient
person over a cliff solves nothing.
'Actually it would have made no difference,' he said.
'Then why are you sorry you didn't do it?'
'Only because I prefer a positive to a negative. In this game that we're playing,
we can't win. Some kinds of failure are better than other kinds, that's all.'
He felt her shoulders give a wriggle of descent She always contradicted him when he said
anything of this kind.
She would not accept it as a law of nature that the individual is always defeated.
In a way she realized that she herself was doomed, that sooner or later the
Thought Police would catch her and kill her, but with another part of her mind
she believed that it was somehow possible to construct a secret world in
which you could live as you chose.
All you needed was luck and cunning and boldness. She did not understand that
there was no such thing as happiness, that the only victory lay in the far
future, long after you were dead, that from the moment of declaring war on the
Party it was better to think of yourself as a corpse.
'We are the dead,' he said.
'We're not dead yet,' said Julia prosaically.
'Not physically. Six months, a year— —five years, conceivably I'm afraid of death.
You were young, so presumably you're more afraid of it than I am. Obviously we
should put it off as long as we can. But it makes very little difference. So long
as human beings stay human, death and life are the same thing.'
'Oh, rubbish! Which would you sooner sleep with, me or a skeleton?
Don't you enjoy being alive? Don't you like feeling: This is me, this is my hand,
this is my leg, I'm real, I'm solid, I'm alive!
Don't you like this?''
She twisted herself around and pressed her bosom against him.
He could feel her breasts, ripe yet firm, through her overalls. Her body seemed to
be pouring some of its youth and vigor into his.
'Yes, I like that,' he said.
'Then stop talking about dying. And now listen to you we've got to fix up about
the next time we meet. We may as well go back to the place in the wood. We've
given it a good long rest. But you must get there by a different way this time.
I've got it all planned out. You take the train— —but look, I'll draw it out for you.'
And in her practical way she scraped together a small square of dust, and with
a twig from a pigeon's nest began drawing a map on the floor